Now that we've seen a few examples of historic ciphers, all of which are badly broken,
现在，我们已经了解了一些历史上的密码，这些密码都已经被攻破，
we're going to switch gears and talk about ciphers that are much better
我们将改变视角，看一些设计得更好的密码。
designed. But before we do that, I want to,
first of all, define more precisely what a
但是在那之前，我想先更精确地定义一下什么是密码。
cipher is. So first of all, a cipher is
actually, remember a cipher is made up of
首先，一个密码实际上是由两个算法构成的。
two algorithms. There's an encryption
algorithm and a decryption algorithm. But
一个加密算法和一个解密算法。但是
in fact, a cipher is defined over a
triple. So the set of all possible keys,
实际上，密码是定义在三元组上的。所以，所有可能的密钥的集合，
which I'm going to denote by script K, and
sometimes I'll call this the key space,
我将用花体的K来表示，有时我会叫它密钥空间
it's the set of all possible keys. There's
this set of all possible messages and this
这是一个包含所有可能的密钥的集合。这里是可能的消息集合，这是可能的
set of all possible ciphertexts. Okay, so
this triple in some sense defines the
密文集合。好，所以这个三元组在某种意义上定义了
environment over which the cipher is
defined. And then the cipher itself is a
这个密码被定义的环境。那么这个密码本身是
pair of efficient algorithms E and D. E is
the encryption algorithm; D is the
一对有效的算法E和D。E是加密算法，D是
decryption algorithm. Of course, E takes
keys and messages. And outputs ciphertexts.
解密算法。当然，E输入的是密钥和消息，输出的是密文。
And the decryption algorithm takes
keys and ciphertexts. Then outputs messages.
解密算法输入的是密钥和密文，输出的是消息。
And the only requirements is that these
algorithms are consistent. They satisfy
这些算法的唯一要求是一致性。它们必须满足
what's called the correctness property. So
for every message in the message space.
正确性。因此对消息空间中的每个消息
And every key in the key space, it had
better be the case that if I encrypt the
和密钥空间的每个密钥，最好的情况是，如果我用密钥K对某个消息进行加密，
message with the key K and then I decrypt
using the same key K I had better get back
那么我用同样的密钥对得到的密文进行解密能够得到原始的消息。
the original message that I started with.
So this equation here is what's called the
那么，这里的这个等式必须成立，称之为
consistency equation and every cipher has
to satisfy it in order to be a cipher
一致性等式。任何一个密码必须满足这个等式，
otherwise it's not possible to decrypt.
One thing I wanted to point out is that I
否则的话就不能解密。这里我想特别指出
put the word efficient here in quotes. And
the reason I do that is because efficient
我给“有效”这里加上引号。之所以这么做，
means different things to different
people. If you're more inclined towards
是因为有效一词对不同的人意义不同。如果你更偏重理论，
theory, efficient means runs in polynomial
time. So algorithms E and D have to run in
“有效”意味着多项式时间。即算法E和D的运行时间相对于
polynomial time in the size of their
inputs. If you're more practically
它们输入的大小必须是多项式的。如果你更偏重于实际
inclined, efficient means runs within a
certain time period. So for example,
有效意味着在能在固定期间内运行。即比如
algorithm E might be required to take
under a minute to encrypt a gigabyte of
可能要求算法E在一分钟内加密1G字节的数据。
data. Now either way, the word efficient
kind of captures both notions and you can
现在无论哪种方式，“有效”都具有这两个方面的含义，你可以
interpret it in your head whichever way
you'd like. I'm just going to keep
随便按你喜欢的想法来解释。我现在只想指出
referring to it as efficient and put
quotes in it as I said if you're theory
带引号的“有效”对于偏重理论的你而言可以理解为
inclined think of it as polynomial time,
otherwise think of it as
是多项式时间，否则把它想成一个
concrete time constraints. Another comment
I want to make is in fact algorithm E.
时间限制也行。另外一点，我想提示大家，这个算法E
It's often a randomized algorithm. What
that means is that as your encrypting
实际上经常是一个随机算法。这个意味着当你加密
messages, algorithm E is gonna generate
random bits for itself, and it's going to
消息的时候，算法E会生成一些随机比特，它会
use those random bits to actually encrypt
the messages that are given to it. On the
用这些比特加密要被处理的消息。另一方面
other hand the decrypting algorithm is
always deterministic. In other words given
解密算法一般是确定性的。换句话说，已知
the key and the ciphertext output is
always the same. Doesn't depend on any
密钥和密文，输出永远是相同的。不依赖于任何
randomness that's used by the algorithm.Okay, so now that we understand what a
算法的随机性。好，我们现在对密码的理解
cipher is better, I want to kind of show
you the first example of a secure cipher.
更深入了一些，现在我想讲一下安全的密码的首个例子。
It's called a one time pad It was designed
by Vernam back at the beginning of the
它叫做一次一密。是Vernam在
twentieth century. Before I actually
explain what the cipher is, let's just
20世纪初设计的。在我正式解释这个密码前，让我们
state it in the terminology that we've
just seen. So the message space for the
先用我们刚定义的术语研究一下这个密码。Vernam一次一密的
Vernam cipher for the one-time pad is the
same as the ciphertext space which is
消息空间和密文空间一样，是
just the set of all n bit binary strings.
This, this just means all sequences of
n长二元字符串的集合。这意味着比特序列，
bits, of zero one characters. The key
space is basically the same as the message
也就是是01字符串。密钥空间基本和消息空间
space which is again simply the n bit of
all binary strings. So a key in the one
一样，是n位二元字符串集合。所以，一次一密中的密钥
time pad is simply a random big string,
it's a random sequence of bits. That's as
就是简单的随机串，是随机比特序列。和待加密的消息
long as the message to be encrypted, as
long as the message. Okay, now that we've
长度一样。好，现在我们已经
specified kind of what's the cipher's
defined over we can actually specify how
知道了这个密码被定义的环境，其实我们也已经知道了
the cipher works and it's actually really
simple. So essentially the ciphertexts.
这个密码的操作方式，它其实是很简单的。所以，基本上密文
Which is the result of encrypting a
message with a particular key, is simply
是用特定密钥加密消息的结果，就是
the XOR of the two. Simply K XOR M. [inaudible] see a quick example of
两者的简单异或。即K异或M.我们来快速看一个例子
this. Remember that XOR, this plus
with a circle. XOR means addition
回忆异或，就是带圆圈的加号，异或
modulo two. So if I take a particular
message, say, 0110111. And it take a
就是模2加。如果我有一个特定的消息，比如说，0110111.取一个
particular key, say 1011001. When I
compute the encryption of the message
特定的密钥，比如说，1011001.当我用这个密钥加密
using this key, all I do is I
compute the XOR of these two
这个消息，我所要做的就是算这两个
strings. In other words, I do addition
module or two bit by bit. So I get one,
字符串的异或。换句话说，我进行逐比特进行模2加。所以我得到1
one, zero, one, one, one, zero. That's a
ciphertext. And then how do I decrypt? I
1,0,1,1,1,0。这就是密文。那我怎么解密呢？我
guess they could do kind of the same
thing. So they decrypt a cipher text using
猜一样的做法。就是用特定密钥来解密密文。
a particular key. What I do is I XOR the
key and the ciphertext again. And so all
我要做的就是把密钥和密文再异或一次。这样，
we have to verify is that it satisfies the
consistency requirements. And I'm going to
我们需要确认的就是满足一致性要求。我将再慢慢
do this slowly once and then from now on
I'm going to assume this is all, simple to
做一次，然后我觉得这个对你们来说就很容易理解了。
you. So we're gonna make, we're gonna have
to make sure that if I decrypt a cipher
我们将要确保如果我对这个密文解密，
text, that was encrypted using a
particular key, I had better get. Back the
用加密时的那个特定密钥，要得到原始
message M. So what happens here? Well,
let's see. So if I look at the encryption
消息M。这是怎么做到的呢？好，我们来看。如果我考虑一下k和m的加密过程，
of k and m, this is just k XOR m by
definition. What's the decryption of k XOR
按照定义只是k和m异或，那k和m的异或用k进行解密是什么呢？
m using k? That's just k XOR (k XOR
m). And so since I said that XOR is
就是k异或（k异或m）。这样，我说过，异或是
addition modulo two, addition is
associative, so this is the same as (k XOR k)
模2加，加法具有交换律，所以这个等于（k异或k）异或m，
XOR m, which is simply as you know k XOR k is a zero, and zero XOR anything
当然你知道k异或k是零，零异或任何数
is simply m. Okay, so this actually shows
that the one-time pad is in fact a cipher,
就是m。好，这个过程就证明了一次一密就是个密码。
but it doesn't say anything about the
security of the cipher. And we'll talk
但是，对这个密码的安全没有做任何说明。现在，我们就要讨论
about security of the cipher in just a
minute. First of all, let me quickly ask
一下这个密码的安全性。首先，让我迅速地
you a question, just to make sure we're
all in sync. Suppose you are given a
给你提个问题，确认我们大家同步。假设给你一个
message m and the encryption of that
message using the one time pad. So all
消息m和相应用一次一密加密的密文。
you're given is the message and the cipher
text. My question to you is, given this
所以，你已知的是消息和密文。我的问题是，已知这一对
pair m and c, can you actually figure out
the one-time pad key that was used in the
m和c，你能从m得到c的过程中推算出一次一密的
creation of c from m?
密钥吗？
So I hope all of you
realize that in fact, given the message in
我希望你们都能意识到，实际上，已知明文相对应
the cipher text it's very easy to recover
what the key is. In particular the key is
的密文，要恢复出密钥是相当容易的。这里，密钥就是
simply M XOR C. Then we'll see that if
it's not immediately obvious to you we'll
M异或C。那么我们来看看，如果你们觉得这种情况不是很显然
see why that's, the case, a little later
in the talk, in the lecture. Okay alright
我们会在这一讲的后面提到。好，
so the 1-time pad is a really cool from a
performance point of view all you're doing
从操作性能来讲，一次一密是很不错的，你要做的就是
is you exo-ring the key in the message so
it's a super, super fast. Cypher for
对密钥和消息进行异或，所以，对于加密和解密
encrypting and decrypting very long
messages. Unfortunately it's very
很长的消息，它非常非常快。但是，不幸的是，在实际当中
difficult to use in practice. The reason
it's difficult to use is the keys are
很难使用。很难使用的原因在于，密钥
essentially as long as the message. So if
Alice and Bob want to communicate
基本上要和消息一样长才行。那么，如果Alice和Bob要安全地通信
securely, so you know Alice wants to send
a message end to Bob, before she begins
也就是，你知道Alice要给Bob发消息，在她开始
even sending the first bit of the message,
she has to transmit a key to Bob that's as
发第一个比特之前，她必须给Bob传一个
long as that message. Well, if she has a
way to transmit a secure key to Bob that's
和消息一样长的密钥。如果她有办法传一个和消息一样长的安全密钥
as long as the message, she might as well
use that same mechanism to also transmit
她就能用同样的方法传这个消息了。
the message itself. So the fact that the
key is as long as the message is quite
所以，实际上让密钥和消息一样长是
problematic and makes the one-time pad
very difficult to use in practice.
很有问题的，使得一次一密在实际当中很难使用。
Although we'll see that the idea behind
the one-time pad is actually quite useful
尽管我们在后面会看到一次一密背后的思想还是十分有用的。
and we'll see that a little bit later. But
for now I want to focus a little bit on
但是现在，我还是把重点放在安全性讨论上。
security. So the obvious questions are,
you know, why is the one-time pad secure?
这儿有个很明显的问题，为什么一次一密是安全的？
Why is it a good cypher? Then to answer
that question, the first thing we have to
为什么它是一个好密码？那么，为了回答这个问题，首先我们要
answer is, what is a secure cipher to
begin with? What is a, what makes cipher
回答的是，一个安全的密码是什么？什么使得
secure? Okay, so the study, security of
ciphers, we have to talk a little bit
密码安全？好，为了学习密码的安全性，我们必须讨论一点
about information theory. And in fact the
first person, to study security of ciphers
信息论。事实上，严格地研究密码安全性的第一个人
rigorously. Is very famous, you know, the
father of information theory, Claude
非常有名，就是信息论之父，Claude Shannon
Shannon, and he published a famous paper
back in 1949 where he analyzes the
在1949年他发表了一篇著名的论文分析
security of the one-time pad. So the idea
behind Shannon's definition of security is
一次一密的安全性。好了，香农对安全性的定义是这样的：
the following. Basically, if all you get
to see is the cypher text, then you should
基本上就是，如果你看到密文，那么你应该对明文
learn absolutely nothing about the plain
text. In other words, the cypher text
绝对一无所知。换句话来说，密文应该不会
should reveal no information about the
plain text. And you see why it took
揭示明文的任何信息。
someone who invented information theory to
come up with this notion because you have
你会明白为什么一个发明信息论的人会提出这个概念
to formulize, formally explain what does
information about the plain text actually
因为你必须公式化地，正式地解释明文的信息表示什么。
mean. Okay so that's what Shannon did and
so let me show you Shannon's definition,
好了，这就是香农干的，让我给你看看香农的定义。
I'll, I'll write it out slowly first. So
what Shannon said is you know suppose we
我来慢慢地把它写出来先。香农说的是，你知道，和前面一样，假如我们
have a cypher E D that's defined over
triple K M and C just as before. So KM and
有一个定义在三元组K、M和C上的密码ED。所以K、M和
C define the key space, the message space
and the cypher text space. And when we say
C定义了密钥空间，消息空间和密文空间。当我们
that the cypher text sorry we say that the
cypher has perfect secrecy if the
说密文，抱歉，当我们说密码具有完善保密性
following condition holds. It so happens
for every two messages M zero and M1 in
如果以下条件成立。对明文空间的任何两个消息M0和M1
the message space. For every two messages
the only requirement I'm gonna put on
这样两个消息，唯一的要求就是它们有
these messages is they have the same
length. Yeah so we're only, we'll see why
相同的长度。是的，我们只需要，
this requirement is necessary in just a
minute. And for every cyphertext, in the
我们马上就会看到这个要求是必要的。还有，对密钥空间中的每个密文也是如此。
cyphertext space. Okay? So for every pair
of method messages and for every cipher
对每一个明文密文对，（满足以下等式）
text, it had better be the case that, if I
ask, what is the probability that,
最好的情况是，如果我问，有多大概率
encrypting M zero with K, woops.
Encrypting M zero with K gives C, okay? So
用k对m0加密，呃，用k对m0加密得到C，好吧？
how likely is it, if we pick a random key?
How likely is it that when we encrypt M
那么，有多大的可能，如果我们选一个随机密钥，有多大的概率我们加密m0，
zero, we get C. That probability should be
the same as when we encrypt N1. Okay, so
得到c。这个概率应该和我们加密m1得到c的情况一样。
the probability of encrypting m one and
getting c is exactly the same as the
所以，我们加密m1得到c的概率应该
probability of encrypting m zero and
getting c. And just as I said where the
和加密m0得到c的概率相等。我刚才说
key, the distribution, is over the
distribution on the key. So, the key is
密钥，密钥分布在密钥空间上。所以，密钥是在密钥空间
uniform in the key space. So k is uniform
in k. And I'm often going to write k arrow
是均匀分布的.所以k在K上是均匀分布的，我一般写k箭头
with a little r above it to denote the
fact that k is a random variable that's
上面带个小r来表示k是一个随机变量
uniformly sampled in the key space k.
Okay, this is the main part of Shannon's
在空间K上均匀分布。好，这是香农定义的主要部分。
definition. And let's think a little bit
about what this definition actually says.
现在，让我们再看一下这个定义是在说什么。
So what does it mean that these two
probabilities are the same? Well, what it
那么，这两个概率相等是什么意思？好，它是说，
says is that if I'm an attacker and I
intercept a particular cypher text c, then
如果我是一个攻击者，我拦截了一个特定的密文C，那么
in reality, the probability that the
cypher text is the encryption of M zero is
现实中，这个密文是M0的加密密文和
exactly the same as the probability that
it's the incryption of M one. Because
是m1的加密密文的概率是一样的。因为
those probabilities are equal. So if I
have, all I have the cypher text C that's
这两个概率是相等的。所以，如果我有，而且仅有截获到的密文C
all I have intercepted I have no idea
whether the cypher text came from M zero
那么我根本不知道密文是m0的密文
or the cypher text came from M one because
again the probability of getting C is
还是m1的密文，因为，再一次，因为对m1和
equally likely whether M zero is being
encrypted or M one is being encrypted. So
m0加密得到c的概率是相等的。
here, we have the definition stated again.
And I just wanna write these properties
所以这里，我们重申了一下这个定义。我想把这些性质
again more precisely. So let's write this
again. So what [inaudible] definition
再写得更清楚一些。让我们把这个再写一遍。所以，这个定义
means is that if I am given a particular
cipher text, I can't tell where it came
表示，如果给我一个特定的密文，我不能分辨它使从
from. I can't tell if it's, if the message
that was encrypted. Is either M zero or M
哪儿来的。我无法得知它是哪个消息加密而来的。是m0还是m1？
one and in fact, this property is true for
all messages. For all these M zero, for
实际上，这个性质对所有的消息都成立。对所有的m0
all M zero and M ones. So not only can I
not tell if'c' came from M zero or M one,
对所有的m0和m1.我不仅仅不能分辨c是m0还是m1的密文，
I can't tell if it came from N two or N
three or N four or N five because all of
我也不能分辨它是m2或者m3或者m4的密文，因为所有
them are equally likely to produce the
cypher text'c'. So what this means really
的明文生成密文C的概率相同。这其实是说
is that if you're encrypting messages with
a one time pad then in fact the most
如果你用一次一密加密消息，那最强的攻击者
powerful adversary, I don't really care
how smart you are, the most powerful
我不管你有多聪明，最厉害的
adversary. Can learn nothing about the
plain text, learns nothing about the plain
攻击者，也不可能知道关于明文的任何信息，不可能从密文知道任何关于
text. From the cypher text. So to say it
iM one more way, basically what this
明文的信息。所以从另一个角度来说，
proves is that there's no, there's no
cypher text-only attack on a cypher that
证明了如果具有完善保密性，那对密码的唯密文攻击是不存在的。
has perfect secrecy. Now, cypher attacks
actually aren't the only attacks possible.
现在，密码攻击不止是唯密文攻击。
And in fact, other attacks may be
possible, other attacks may be possible.
实际上，其它攻击也存在，也存在其它攻击。
Okay. Now that we understand what perfect
secrecy, means, the question is, can we
好，现在让我们来理解一下完善保密性，也就是说，问题是
build ciphers that actually have perfect
secrecy? And it turns out that we don't
我们能构造具有完善保密性的密码吗？结果是我们不需要再研究多深入
have to look very far, the one time
pattern fact has perfect secrecy. So I
一次一密就具备完善保密性。所以，我
want to prove to you this is Shannon's first
results and I wanna prove this fact to
想给大家证明一下香农的第一个结论，我想给大家证明的这个事实
you, it's very simple proof so let's go
ahead and look at it and just do it. So we
它其实是个十分简单的证明，所以让我们继续做做看。
need to kind of interpret what does that
mean, what is this probability that E K M
我们需要简单解释一下E（k，m0）=c的概率是什么。
Zero is equal to C. So it's actually not that
hard to see that for every message and
实际上不难看出，对于每一个消息和每一个
every cyphertext the probability that the
encryption of N under a key K the
每一个密文，在密钥k下对m加密等于c
probability that, that's equal to C, the
probability that our random choice of key
的概率，就是我们随机选择密钥K的概率
by definition. All that is, is basically
the number of keys. Okay, instruct Key.
根据定义，这就是，密钥的个数，k，属于K。
Such that, well. If I encrypt. And with k
I get c. So I literally count the number
这样，如果我加密，用k加密得到c。所以，我就是数一下密钥的
of keys and I divide by the total number
of keys. Right? That's what it means, that
个数，除以密钥的个数，对吧？这就是它的含义，
if I choose a random key, that key maps m
to c. Right. So it's basically the number
如果我随机选择密钥，密钥将m映射到c。好的，这就是
of key that map m to c divided by the
total number of keys. This is its
能将消息m映射到c的密钥的个数除以密钥总数。这就是这个
probability. So now suppose that we had a
cypher such that for all messages and all
概率。所以现在，假设我们有一个密码，对所有消息和
cypher texts, it so happens that if I look
at this number, the number of k, k, and k,
密文，如果看这个个数，k的个数，k属于K，
such that e, k, m is equal to c. In other
words, I'm looking at the number of keys
使得E（k，m）=c。换句话说，我在找能使
that map m to c. Suppose this number
happens to be a constant. So say it
消息m映射成密文c的密钥的个数。假设这个数恰好是个常数，假如说
happens to be two, three, or ten or
fifteen. It just hap, happens to be an
恰好就是2,3,或者10或15，它恰好是个
absolute constance. If that's the case,
then by definition, for all m0 and m1 and
常数，如果是这种情况，根据定义，对于所有的m0和m1
for all c, this probability has to be the
same because the denominator is the same,
和c，这个概率必须相同，因为分母相同，
the numerator is the same, it's just as
constant, and therefore the probability is
分子也相同，它恰好是个常数，因此，这个概率
always the same for all m and c. And so if
this property is true, then the cypher has
对所有的m和c相同。如果这个性质是正确的，那么这个密码
to have, the cypher has perfect secrecy.
Okay, so lets see what can we say about
必然是完善保密的。好了，让我们看一下一次一密的这个量值。
this quantity for the one time pad. So the
sec-, so, the question to you is, if I
所以现在，我们的问题是，如果我
have a message in a cipher-text, how many
one time pad keys are there [inaudible]
有一个消息的密文，一次一密中有多少个密钥，
map, this message ends, so the [inaudible]
C? So, in other words, how many keys are
能把这个消息m映射成c，所以，换句说，
there, such that M XOR K is equal to C?
So I hope you've all answered one. And
有多少个密钥能使m异或k得到c？我希望你们的答案是1。
let's see why that's the case. For the one
time pad, if we have that, the encryption
那么我们来看看为什么是这样。对于一次一密来说，如果我们有
of K of M under K is equal to C. But
basically, well, by definition, that
对消息m用密钥k加密得到c，但是，基本上，根据定义
implies that K XOR M is equal to C. But
that also simply says that K has to equal
这个意味着k异或m等于c。但是它也简单地表示k等于
to M XOR C. Yes, I just X over both
sides by M and I get that K must equal the
m异或c。是的，我只需要在这两边同时异或m就得到k等于
M XOR C. Okay? So what that says is
that, for the one time pad, in fact, the
m异或c，对吧？所以，这里是说，对于一次一密，实际上，
number of keys, in K, shows the EKM, is
equal to C. That simply is one, and this
密钥的个数，K中的密钥个数，满足E（k，m）=c，就是1.而且
holds for all messages in cipher text. And
so, again, by what we said before, it just
这对所有的密文和消息都成立。所以，和我们前面说的一样，
says that the one time pad has, perfect
secrecy. Perfect secrecy and that
这说明一次一密具有完善保密性。完善保密性和
completes the proof of this [inaudible]
very, very simple. Very, very simple
完善保密性的证明非常、非常简单。这是一个很简单的
lemma. Now the funny thing is that
even though this lemma is so simple to
引理。有趣的是，虽然这个引理的证明非常
prove in fact it proves a pretty powerful
statement again. This basically says for
简单，但是它能证明一个很强的结论。它说明
the one time [inaudible] there is no
cypher text only attack. So, unlike the
对于一次一密，没有唯密文攻击。所以不像
substitution cipher, or the vigenere
cipher, or the rotor machines, all those
代换密码，或者维吉尼亚密码，或者转轮机，
could be broken by ciphertext-only attack.
We've just proved that for the one-time
这些密码都能被唯密文攻击破译，我们刚证明了一次一密
pad, that's simply impossible. Given the
cyphertext, you simply learn nothing about
就是不能进行唯密文攻击。已知密文，你就是不能获得
the plaintext. However, as we can see,
this is simply not the end of the story. I
任何有关明文的消息。然而，如你所见，这并非故事的结局。
mean, are we done? I mean, basically,
we're done with the course now, cuz we
我是说，我们结束了吗？我的意思是，我们关于密码这门课学完了吗？
have a way. To encrypt, so that an
attacker can't recover anything about our
因为我们有办法，对一个消息加密，而攻击者无法破译。
method. So maybe we're done with the
course. But in fact, as we'll see, there
所以有可能，我们学完了。但是实际上，后面我们会看到
are other attacks. And, in fact, the one
time pad is actually not such a
还有其它的攻击。而且，事实上，一次一密并不是
secure cipher. And in fact, there are
other attacks that are possible, and we'll
一种安全的密码。事实是，还有其他可能的攻击，我们很快
see that shortly. Okay? I emphasize again
the fact that it has perfect secrecy does
就会讲到。这里我再次强调，具备完善保密性并不
not mean that the one time pad is the
secure cypher to use. Okay. But as we said
意味着一次一密是一个安全可用的密码。好，但是我们前面
the problem with the one time pad is that
the secret key is really long. If you had
说过一次一密的问题在于，密钥实在太长了。如果你有
a way of. Communicating the secret key
over to the other side. You might as well
办法在通信双方协商秘密密钥，你就可以用同样
use that exact same method to also
communicate the message to the other side,
的方法进行消息通信。
in which case you wouldn't need a cypher
to begin with. Okay? So the problem again
这种情况下，你根本就不用密码了，好吧？所以问题又出现了，
is the one time pad had really long keys
and so the obvious question is are there
一次一密有很长的密钥，显而易见的问题是，有没有其他
other cyphers that has perfect secrecy and
possibly have much, much shorter keys?
其它密钥具备完善保密性，而且可能只有较短的密钥？
Well, so the bad news is the Shannon,
after proving that the one-time pad has
好，坏消息是，香农证完一次一密有
perfect secrecy, proved another theorem
that says that in fact if a cypher has
完善保密性后，证明了另外一个定理，这个定理说，实际上，如果一个密码
perfect secrecy, the number of keys in the
cypher must be at least the number of
具备完善保密性，那么密钥的个数至少要和这个密码
messages that the cypher can handle. Okay,
so in particular, what this means is if I
要加密的消息一样多。好，特别地，这意味着
have perfect secrecy. Then necessarily the
number of keys, or rather the length of my
如果我具备完善保密性，那么密钥个数，或者我密钥的长度
key, must be greater than the length of
the message. So, in fact, since the one
必须比消息长度要大。实际上，因为一次
time pad satisfies us with equality, the
one time pad is an optimal, cipher that
一密满足这里的等号，所以，一次是一种最优的具备
has perfect secrecy, okay? So basically,
what this shows is that this is an
完善保密性的密码，好吧？这是一个很，
interesting notion. The one time pad is an
interesting cipher. But, in fact, in
有趣的概念。一次一密是一个很有趣的密码。但是，事实上，
reality, it's actually quite hard to use.
It's hard to use in practice, again,
在现实中，它很难被实际应用。因为它的长密钥，使得它在
because of these long keys. And so this
notion of perfect secrecy, even though
实际中很难用。所以，完善保密性这个概念，尽管它
it's quite interesting, basically says
that it doesn't really tell us the
很有趣，但是，它基本上不能告诉我们
practical cyphers are going to be secure.
And we're gonna see, but, as we said, the
实际当中的密码是否安全。尽管如此，我们会看到，我们前面说过
idea behind the one time pad is quite good.
And we're gonna see, in the next lecture,
一次一密背后的想法是很好的。我们将会看到，下一节，
how to make that into a practical
system.
我们怎么样把这种想法做成一个实用的系统。